<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discovery of subterraneall treasure viz. of all manner of mines and mineralls, from the gold to the coale; with plaine directions and rules for the finding of them in all kingdoms and countries. And also the art of melting, refining, and assaying of them is plainly declared, so that every ordinary man, that is indifferently capacious, may with small change presently try the value of such oares as shall be found either by rule or by accident. Whereunto is added a reall experiment whereby every ignorant man may presently try whether any peece of gold that shal come to his hands be true or connterfeit [sic] ... Also a perfect way to try what colour any berry, leafe, flower, stalke, root, fruit, seed, barke, or wood will give: with a perfect way to make colours that they shall not stayne nor fade like ordinary colours. ...</title>
            <author>Plattes, Gabriel, fl. 1638-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09740</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100866</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836693</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836693</idno>
            <idno type="VID">978</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09740)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 978)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1181:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discovery of subterraneall treasure viz. of all manner of mines and mineralls, from the gold to the coale; with plaine directions and rules for the finding of them in all kingdoms and countries. And also the art of melting, refining, and assaying of them is plainly declared, so that every ordinary man, that is indifferently capacious, may with small change presently try the value of such oares as shall be found either by rule or by accident. Whereunto is added a reall experiment whereby every ignorant man may presently try whether any peece of gold that shal come to his hands be true or connterfeit [sic] ... Also a perfect way to try what colour any berry, leafe, flower, stalke, root, fruit, seed, barke, or wood will give: with a perfect way to make colours that they shall not stayne nor fade like ordinary colours. ...</title>
                  <author>Plattes, Gabriel, fl. 1638-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By I. Okes, for Iasper Emery, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Eagle and Child in Pauls Church-yard next Watlin-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC XXXIX [1639]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Gabriel Plattes.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which give signatures: [A]²  B-I⁴ K² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Metallurgy --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dyes and dyeing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mineralogy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Chemistry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:978:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:978:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:978:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:978:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Diſcovery of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terraneall Treaſure, viz. Of all manner of
<hi>Mines</hi> and <hi>Mineralls,</hi> from the <hi>Gold</hi> to the
<hi>Coale;</hi> with plaine Directions and Rules for the finding of them in all
Kingdomes and Countries. And alſo the <hi>Art</hi> of Melting, Refining, and
Aſſaying of them is plainly declared, ſo that every ordinary man, that is
indifferently capacious, may with ſmall charge preſently try the value of
ſuch <hi>Oares</hi> as ſhall be found either by rule or by accident.
<hi>Whereunto is added a reall Experiment whereby every ignorant man may
preſently try whether any peece of Gold that ſhal come to his hands be true
or counterfeit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out defacing or altering the forme thereof, and more
certainly than any Gold-ſmith or Refiner could for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly diſcerne.</hi>
Alſo a perfect way to try what colour any Berry, Leafe, Flower, Stalke, Root,
Fruit, Seed, Barke, or Wood will give: with a perfect way to make Colours that
they ſhall not ſtayne nor fade like ordinary Colours. <hi>Very
neceſſary for every one to know, whether he be Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailer by Land or Sea,
or in what Country, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, or plantation ſoever hee ſhall
Inhabite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>I. Okes,</hi> for <hi>Iaſper
Emery,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Eagle and
Child in Pauls Church-yard next Watlin-ſtreet. MDCXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:978:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur: Tho. VVykes. February 19. 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:978:3"/>
            <head>TO HIS VVORTHY FRIEND MASTER William Englebert
<hi>Eſquire.</hi> Health, and Happineſſe Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and Eternall, is
heartily wiſhed.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He goodneſſe of your diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath brought you to
this trouble and paines at this time, to peruſe theſe Lines; by giving me
ſo free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly your Iudicious approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my former labours: now you have
gotten a Cuſtomer of mee, for the like courteſie to bee renewed; for which
I ſhall bee bound in a double Bond.</p>
            <p>When I reade the words of our SAVIOVR CHRIST, after hee had fed
ſuch a number of people with a few Loaves and Fiſhes, <hi>viz.</hi> How hee
Commanded the broken Meate to bee gathered up carefully that nothing be loſt;
when as hee could (no doubt) have made an hundred times as much with a word
ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: I conceived that it was done for a patterne of frugality, to
ſhew us how carefull
<pb facs="tcp:978:4"/>wee ought to bee in the preſervation of ſuch things
from loſſe, which are ordained to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve and ſuſtaine the lives of
Men: therefore I being from my Child-hood a ſtrict obſerver of the great
loſſe that came to this Country, partly through ignorance, and partly
through negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, in rayſing that benefit out of the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall, and
ſubterraneall Treaſures of the Earth, ordained of GOD (no doubt) for the
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe and ſuſtenance of mens livings; thought that I could not bee
better employed, then to advertiſe the World thereof, and to Divulge my
knowledge, and experience in theſe affaires for the common profit; dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
my ſelfe obliged thereunto; for that it hath pleaſed GOD to give a large
bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to my long labours, and Charges ſpent in theſe and ſuch
like affaires.</p>
            <p>Alſo when I heard the manifold complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of indigent people,
of the hardneſſe of the World, and of the difficultie of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining their
livings: I have knowne many people of indifferent vertuous diſpoſitions,
for very want of meanes, to take in hand ſome actions which were not
laudable.</p>
            <p>Theſe with divers other Motives have beene ſpurres to mee, to
Publiſh not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Booke of the diſcovery of Subterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall
Treaſures; but alſo my other Booke, mentioned in the Preface enſuing, of
the Diſcovery of hidden Treaſures in the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of the Earth: Both
which Bookes, if they
<pb facs="tcp:978:4"/>ſhall bee diligently peruſed, and induſtriouſly
practiſed; will adminiſter ſufficient cure for all the Maladies before
mentioned.</p>
            <p>Now whereas the Cuſtome is to make choice of a Patron to protect
the Author from the Calumniations of malevolent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; yea, though
experience her ſelfe (the Miſtreſſe of Art) ſhall be ready as an
Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, to manifeſt the truth of his aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for that opinion is
generally Deified, and almoſt every where ſwayeth all; and this worthy
Miſtris Experience (which ſuffereth no impoſture to raigne) is many times
lightly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and thruſt out of the doores.</p>
            <p>I therefore beſeech you once againe to lend mee your grave
Judgement, and approbation, ripened by threeſcore yeares practice, and
expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, in things partly of this nature, which I will make bold to put
into the Ballance, to over-weigh the ignorance, and unskilfulneſſe of all
detractors whatſoever; making no queſtion, but that as Thunder and
Lightning cauſed <hi>Heliogabalus</hi> to creepe into an hole:
notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his boldneſſe, and hardneſſe in calme weather: In
like manner ſo manifeſt experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will drive away all Sophiſticall
oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. So I humbly take my leave</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your bounden Servant, <hi>Gabriel
Plattes.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:978:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas divers reaſons have joyned together to move mee to take
in hand this Taske: I will declare ſome few of thoſe that may give the
beſt ſatiſfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Reader, in this manner following. Firſt, when
I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the great number of Treaſure and riches which lyeth hidden in
the belly of the Earth, and doth no good at all: and alſo the great benefit
which might accrew to divers Kingdomes and Countries, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting people on
worke; not onely in the diſcovering of them, but alſo in the ſeverall
opperations about the digging, melting, and refining of them: alſo when J
conſidered that the moſt part of the Mines hitherto diſcovered have come
by meere accident: I thought that J could not be better employed, than to give
Rules and Directions for the ſame: for though it is not unpoſſible, that
if two men be ſent to ſeeke a thing that is loſt, and one of them bee
hudwinked, and the other have the uſe and benefit of his eyes, yet the
perſon hudwinked may caſually ſtumble upon it; nevertheleſſe it is
twenty to one
<pb facs="tcp:978:5"/>that the other ſhould have found it before him: ſo
in this caſe, I dare hazard a Wager of twenty to one, that there will bee
more good Mines diſcovered within ſeven yeares after the divulging of
theſe Rules and directions, than hath beene in twenty-ſeven yeares before:
Alſo when I conſidered that many Mineralls found out by accident, have come
to no good by reaſon of the diſtance of place from Refiners, and men of
judgement and experience: for that the finders thereof were loath to come ſo
farre, and ſpend ſo much money upon an uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at the triall thereof
would require: I thought I could not doe a better deede, than to ſhew the
man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſuch trials in ſuch plaine manner that every man may try the
ſame in his Ship, or Chimney Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with little coſt and labour.</p>
            <p>And the truth of this I can witneſſe by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for when
I was a youth, and had no skill in theſe affaires; I happened upon a Minerall
faire to ſee to, and could find no man neerer than an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred miles which
could enforme me of the true value thereof: whereupon, rather then to be at
ſuch char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as the triall required, I ſuffered the ſame to bee
neglected.</p>
            <p>And though that the rules and directions given in this Booke bee
exquiſite, and give ſtrong ſignes of Mettalls and Mineralls; yet I would
bee loath that any man ſhould be thereby animated no take in hand great
Voyages, and conſume his Eſtate in the purſuite of this deſigne;
deeming them to bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible ever to faile: but rather to make this a
<pb facs="tcp:978:6"/>part of his buſineſſe, when hee ſhall come to
ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as yeeld ſtrong probabilities.</p>
            <p>And ſo farre I am from envying the former wayes in finding them
by accident, that I have part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken this paines; that thoſe which ſhall
hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bee found by accident may not bee neglected as I conjecture, that
many have beene by my owne formerly mentioned.</p>
            <p>For I could wiſh that many men had the like for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune that one
had, who in the climbing up of the great Mountaine called <hi>Poterſee,</hi>
in the Kingdome of <hi>Perue</hi> in the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> tooke hold of
a young Tree to ſtay himſelfe withall; and thereby plucked it up by the
rootes, whereunto there did adheare good Silver Oare; which being tried and
found rich, hath ever ſince beene wrought upon: and innumerable treaſure
and riches have therehence beene digged, to the valew of many hundred Millions
of pounds Sterling.</p>
            <p>And to the end I may no longer ſtay the Reader with Preambles, I
will divide my booke into <hi>12.</hi> Chapters, like as I did my Booke Printed
<hi>Anno. Dom. 1638.</hi> Entituled, <hi>A diſcovery of hidden
Treaſure:</hi> wiſhing all thoſe that deſire to be skilfull in theſe
affaires; to take a little paines to read that Booke, which differeth from this
no otherwayes, but as the Art of Surgery differeth from the Art of Phyſicke:
for as Surgeons deale chiefly with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall parts of mans body, yet
ſtand in need of the knowledge of all the parts; and as Phyſitians chiefly
deale with the internall parts, yet cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:978:6"/>the knowledge of the exterttall parts: So though that
Booke treate wholly upon the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Treaſures hidden in the
ſuperficies and exurball parts of the Terreſtriall Globe, yet the knowledge
of many things therein contained are very conducible to make a skilfull
Mineraliſt, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you further to underſtand, that if any good will bee
done at all, it will bee done with a ſmall Charge: and with ſomewhat
leſſe than before this Booke was publiſhed; if you obſerve the Contents
thereof adviſedly: So I take my leave and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your hearty Well-wiſher. G.
P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>CHAP.</hi> 1.</label> Wherein is ſhewed by a playne
De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration the naturall cauſe of the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and production of
Mountaynes and Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals: whereby the Seekers may obtayn a good competent
meaſure of knowledge to guide them where to ſeek for the other external
ſigns.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:978:7"/>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.</label> Wherein is ſhewed the ſignes
of Mines and Minerals, with the manner how to worke to find the ſame.
<hi>pag.</hi> 9</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.</label> Now that we are come to the
melting and refining of <hi>Metals,</hi> I will begin firſt with the <hi>Oare
of Lead,</hi> becauſe that is one of the moſt common <hi>Metalls</hi> found
in theſe <hi>Northern Countries. p.</hi> 14</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.</label> Wherein is ſhewed the
operations <hi>for Tinns. pa.</hi> 20</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 5:</label> Wherin is ſhewed the
operations <hi>of Jron. pa.</hi> 24</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.</label> Wherein is ſhewed the
operations <hi>of Copper. p.</hi> 26</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.</label> Wherein is ſhewed the
operations of <hi>Silver. pa.</hi> 30</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.</label> Wherein is ſhewed the
operations of <hi>Gold:</hi> and reall experiments whereby any man may
preſently trye whether any peece of Gold be true or counterfeit, without
defacing or alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the forme thereof. <hi>pag.</hi> 33</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.</label> Wherein is ſhewed how true and
perfit Gold may be made by <hi>Art,</hi> with loſſe to the workman.
<hi>pag.</hi> 40</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.</label> Wherein is ſhewed the
operations for ſome of the inferiour <hi>Metals. pag.</hi> 44</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.</label> Wherein is ſhewed the wayes
to finde out pit-coales: Alſo the naturall cauſe of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of
them, by a plain demonſtration. <hi>p.</hi> 47</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.</label> Wherein is ſhewed a perfit
way to trye what colour any <hi>Berry, Leafe, Flower, Stalke, Root, Fruit,
Seed, Barke,</hi> or <hi>Wood</hi> will give: Alſo a perfit way to make
colours fixed, which will not abide the ordinary way. <hi>pag.</hi> 52.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:978:7"/>A Diſcovery of all ſorts of Mines and
Minerals.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Wherein is ſhewed by a plaine Demonſtration the naturall
cauſe of the generation and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of Mountaines and Mettals; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
the Seekers may ohtaine a good compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent meaſure of knowledge to guide them
where to ſeeke for the other Externall ſignes.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ALOMON ſayth, that Hope deferred breaks the heart; but the
deſire ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, is a Tree of Life: If Hope onely deferred breake the Heart;
then Hope fruſtrated muſt needs breake it a great deale more.</p>
            <p>To the end therefore that our Hope
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:978:8"/>may not bee too frequently fruſtrated, I will
firſt declare the places where there is no probability to finde out Mettalls,
and afterwards I will ſhew where there is ſtrong probability: and then in
the next Chapter I will ſhew how to goe about the worke, to find out the
ſtrong ſignes which may rightly guide the ſeekers to obtaine their
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
            <p>And firſt, there is no probability that any Mettalls can bee
generated neare unto the North and South poles of the Globe, for thoſe can by
no meanes have any convenient Matrix for ſuch a generation, being by all
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities nothing but two Iſlands of Ice, for if they were any thing
elſe, the courſe of Nature muſt needs alter, and change, and runne
preſently out of order.</p>
            <p>For as there is in the burning Zones a continuall exhalation of
Water, and rarifying of the ſame into Ayre: ſo there muſt needes bee in
the North
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:978:8"/>and South a continuall condenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Aire into
Water to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the ſame againe, elſe the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot bee perpetually
circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</p>
            <p>Now whereas the North and South parts, by reaſon of their
coldneſſe, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſuffer the ſaid condenſed Meteors to deſcend in
forme of Water, but in the forme of Snow, Haile, or ſome ſubſtance of
like nature, which there cannot melt in the ſuperficies for want of heate, it
is very probable that the new Accretion this way produced, doth preſſe
downe ſtill with its weight the ſaid Ilands of Ice towards the Center,
where the centrall heate mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it off continually, by which meanes the
ſphericall forme of both Earth and Water are perpetually pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
            <p>And if any man bee of a contrary opinion, I will not envie him; but
as for my owne part, I will ſell my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and hope of Mettalls in
thoſe places
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:978:9"/>for a Farthing, although I had a device that the
cold there could not prevent my ſeeking for them.</p>
            <p>Alſo in Vallies and plaine Champion Countries, there is no hope to
proſper in this deſigne, for the wombe of ſuch earth is not apt for
ſuch a generation, the Reaſons whereof will preſently fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>Now that wee have left us no other places to ſeeke in but the
rocky Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, I will ſpend the reſt of this Chapter in demonſtrating
the naturall cauſe of the generation of Rocks, Mountaines, and Metalls, and
ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed forward.</p>
            <p>And firſt I will ſet downe the Opinions of others with their
Confutation, and laſtly the confirmation of mine owne Opinion by irrefragable
Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Some have thought that the mighty Creator made the vaſt, deformed,
and craggy Rocks and Mountaines in the beginning, but this appeareth to bee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:978:9"/>an Opinion, whereby great diſhonour may reflect
upon the Creator, who beſides his Omnipotent power, doth continually make
uſe of his admirable Wiſdome, and exquiſite Artifice in all his Workes,
and made nothing defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or unfit for the uſe for which it was created: Now
the Earth being ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to beare Fruits for the uſe of Men, and Rocks are
not fit for that purpoſe, it plainely appeareth that they came by
accident.</p>
            <p>Some others have thought that they came by accident, but yet that
they were produced by accretion in length of time, even as Warts, Tumours,
Wenns, and Excreſcences are engendred in the ſuperficies of mens bodies:
and of this Opinion I my ſelfe was in my minori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, till ſuch time as by
practicall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience I found out a more probable opinion.</p>
            <p>Now for a plaine demonſtration, let this Experiment following bee
tryed, and I make no queſtion, but that it will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:978:10"/>ſatisfie every one that hath an inquiſitive
diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>Let there bee had a great retort of Glaſſe, and let the ſame
be halfe filled with Brimſtone, Sea-coale, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bituminous and
Sulphurious ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terraneall ſubſtances as can bee gotten: then fill the
necke thereof halfe full with the moſt free earth from ſtones that can be
found, but thruſt it not in too hard, then let it bee luted, and ſet in an
open Furnace to diſtill with a temperate Fire, which may onely kindle the
ſaid ſubſtances, and if you worke exquiſitely, you ſhall finde the
ſaid Earth petrified, and turned into a Stone: you ſhall alſo finde
cracks and chinkes in it, filled with the moſt te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacious, clammy, and
viſcous parts of the ſaid vapours, which aſcended from the
ſubterraneall combuſtible ſubſtances.</p>
            <p>Whereby it appeareth that the ſame thing is done by Nature, and
that the Rocks and craggy Mountaines are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:978:10"/>cauſed by the vapours of Bituminous and
Sulphurious ſubſtances kindled in the bowells of the Earth, of which there
bee divers ſo well knowne, that they neede not bee heere mentioned: Alſo it
appeareth that the veines of Mettalls are engendred in the crackes and crannies
of the ſaid Mountaines, out of the moſt clammy and glute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous part of the
ſaid vapours there ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering, where the cold gave them leave to bee congealed
and conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>Now concerning the exaltation of the Mountaines above the Vallies,
it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth to come to paſſe by the water in former times, whoſe
property is to weare away by its motion the moſt looſe earth, and to leave
the more firme ground, and rockie places high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: but whether this was done
by <hi>Noahs</hi> Flood, or by the Sea in former Ages, is doubted. As for my
opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, I referre the Reader to my Booke formerly mentioned, and if
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:978:11"/>any man be in doubt of this, let him take the
Stone formerly made by Art, and place it ſo, that the motion of the water may
worke upon it, and you ſhall finde it worne moſt in the looſeſt places,
and leaſt in the more firme compacted places; thereby ſhewing the naturall
cauſe of Mountaines and Valleyes. Alſo if a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhould bee turned out
of its courſe, and the bottome thereof accurately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered upon, how the
water by his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath worne away the Earth moſt in the looſeſt Earth,
and leaſt in that which is more firme, it doth evidently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the
naturall cauſe of Hills and Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and the unevenneſſe of the Earth
cauſed by the motion of the Sea in former Ages.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:978:11"/>
            <head>CHAP. 2.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Wherein is ſhewed the ſignes of Mines and Minerals, with the
manner how to worke to find the ſame.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen we come to the Rocky and Craggy Mountaynes, the firſt thing
we are to obſerve, is the barrenneſſe of them; For the more bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren they
are; the greater probability there is that they containerich Mines and
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals.</p>
            <p>The next worke is to finde out the Springs of Water iſſuing out
of the ſaid Mountaynes; and thoſe being found, a quantity of the ſayd
water is to be boiled in a new cleane pipkin, to the conſiſtency of thinne
Oyle, but not ſo thicke as a Syrrup, and when it is almoſt cold, then to
put it into an Vrinall, and to ſet it in the coldeſt place that can be
found for 3 daies, then to play the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and to obſerve it
exquiſitly what reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:978:12"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:978:12"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:978:13"/>it yeeldeth: if nothing ſettle but a black
earth or mudde, it is a ſigne of <hi>Coales:</hi> if ſome part thereof
ſhoot into Ice, or a ſubſtance like Ice or Vitrioll, then to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
the colour thereof; if it be greene or blewiſh, it is an evident ſigne of
Copper; if whitiſh, then it may ſignifie any other Mettall without
exception.</p>
            <p>The next worke is to goe to the bare Rocks, and there to finde out
the clifts, cracks, and cranies: this done, to goe to the toppe: or till you
finde ſome Graſſe growing right upon the top of the ſaid Cranies, and
then to obſerve diligently the kinde of that Graſſe, and how it
diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from other Graſſe, ordinarily grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſame Mountaine;
not onely in forme, but alſo in colour, which colour ſheweth the greateſt
difference in the heat of Summer, for the ſubterraneall Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours iſſuing
out of the Orifice of Mines, differ from thoſe which iſſue out of the
more ſolide places of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</p>
            <p>The next worke is to ſee if there bee
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:978:13"/>any marcaſites to be found in the
ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of the ſaid Mountaines: which though they are uſually of
divers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and ſeldome good for any thing, yet they are ſtrong
ſignes of Mineralls within, being themſelves the ſpume and froth of the
better Mettals, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed forth, even as Drinke breatheth up his Yeſt or
Froth to the Superfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p>And theſe if they be put in an ordinary fire, they will turne
blacke, and yeeld a ſmell of <hi>Brimſtone, Arſnicke, Antimony,</hi> or
ſome other thing, commonly called or knowne by the name of a <hi>middle
Minerall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next worke is to trie the operation with the <hi>Virgula
divina,</hi> as beneath is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared: and where it ſheweth the ſtrongeſt
ſignes, as is likewiſe beneath taught: and alſo the place is moſt
accompanyed with the other ſignes formerly mentioned: there by digging or
boaring to try your fortunes.</p>
            <p>The operation with the <hi>Virgula divina</hi> is thus to be
performed: ſome obſerve
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:978:14"/>a ſet day and houre with certaine words and
Ceremonies at the cutting up of the ſame, which I have found to bee little to
the purpoſe: thus I wrought about Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomer, in a calme morning: I cut up a
rod of Haſell, all of the ſame ſprings growth, almoſt a yard long: then
I tyed it to my ſtaffe, in the middle, with a ſtrong thred, ſo that it
did hang even, like the Beame of a Ballance: thus I carryed it up and downe the
Mountaines where Lead growed, and before Noone it gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded mee to the Orifice of
a Lead mine: which I tryed, having one with me with an hacke of Iron and a
Spade; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two houres we found a veine of Lead Oare, within leſſe
than a foot of the graſſe: the ſignes that it ſheweth is to bow down
the root end towards the earth as though it would grow there, neare unto the
Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Mine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when you ſee it doe ſo, you muſt carry it round
about the place, to ſee that it turneth in the ſtring ſtill to the place,
on which ſide ſoever you ſtand.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:978:14"/>
            <p>The reaſon of this attraction I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to bee of Kin to the
Load-ſtone, drawing Iron to it by a ſecret vertue, inbred by nature, and
not by any coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as ſome have fondly imagined.</p>
            <p>And the Reaſon of this my opinion was, becauſe that in divers of
my practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Experiments I have obſerved an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction betwixt ſeverall
things, like that of the Load-ſtone, and Iron; and if it were to good
purpoſe, I ſuppoſe that I could ſhew more experience of that kind than
any man in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the new Plantations, as <hi>New-England, Virginia,
Bermudas,</hi> &amp;c. where it is like that few or none have ever try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that
had any skill in theſe affaires, it is very probable that the Orifice of
divers Mynes may be diſcerned with the eye in the clifts of the Rocks in many
places, as ſome have beene in <hi>England</hi> at the firſt, before that
men grew a little skilfull, and theſe to be loſt and neglected, were a
ſhame to the Planters; for theſe Mynes if they prove rich, would yeeld more

<pb n="14" facs="tcp:978:15"/>gaine in one yeare, than their Tobacco and ſuch
trifles would yeeld in their whole lives.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 3.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Now that wee are come to the melting and refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Mettalls, I
will begin firſt with the Oare of <hi>Lead,</hi> becauſe that is one of the
moſt common Mettalls found in theſe Northerne Countries.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt worke therefore to bee done, is to have a little grate
of Iron about a foot broad, like ſuch as are uſed in a Still to make the
fire upon: this is to be placed in your Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-corner with looſe Bricks,
one thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe underneath, and empty in the middle, to give aire to the
fire; then lay more Bricks above foure courſe high, round about, and if they
be laid without Morter, the fire will burne the better:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:978:15"/>then fill it with Char-coales kindled, in the
middeſt whereof ſet your melting Pot, with one pound of Lead-oare, and
foure ounces of filings of Iron mingled together, and ſo blow to it
ſtrongly with a paire of good hand-bellows, till it be well melted downe;
then let the Pot be taken out with a paire of Tongs, and ſet to coole: when
it is cold, breake it, and knocke off the brittle cinder ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the top of
the Mettall with an Hammer, till none be left but the malle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mettall, which
you may aſſay and refine in this manner following: Take a little Teſt
made as beneath, and place it in the middle of your Chimney; lay aſhes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
it, about ſixe inches broad, and as high, or rather higher than your Teſt:
lay Bricks about the aſhes to hold them up one Brick thickneſſe, and 2.
Bricks broad, then lay about halfe a peck of Char-coales upon the Teſt
kindled, and when they are almoſt conſumed, and the Teſt red-hot, put
them by a little in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt over the Teſt, and lay over a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:978:16"/>peece of good Oake-wood about five in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
ſquare, and eighteene inches long; lay it ſo upon two Tyle-ſheards, that
it may lye about an inch and an halfe above the Teſt, then lay on more
ordinary Billets and ſome Char-coales amongſt: make the fire about ſo
ſtrong as to roaſt a Pigge, then blow to it a little, till the fire burne
cleare, then put upon the Teſt two Ounces of your Lead, and blow to it
gently, and in three quarters of an houre, all the Lead will bee conſumed,
and the Silver will lye in the middle of the Teſt like a little Beade or
Pearle, then put aſide the fire, and let all bee cold.</p>
            <p>Then you may weigh the Silver in a paire of Gold-ſcales, and ſo
caſt it up how much there is in a Tunne of Lead: I have thus tryed many
Oares, and have found them to differ in goodneſſe of all ſorts, from
Forty ſhillings worth of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in a Tunne, to Thirty five pounds worth of
Silver in a Tunne, and there is no Lead but it holded ſome Silver, yet
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:978:16"/>it is not worth the refining, unleſſe it
yeeld eight or tenne pound upon a Tun at the leaſt.</p>
            <p>The Teſt may thus be made: firſt, let a Smith make a Ring of
Iron about foure inches wide, and two inches deepe, and a quarter of an inch
thick, and as wide above as beneath, and without a bottome.</p>
            <p>Then burne Mutton and Beefe-bones in the Fire til they be white,
then beate them ſmal in a Morter, and ſcarce them fine like meale: then
with a little beere or water temper a ſmall part thereof like pappe, then put
to ſo much more of the dry powder by little and little, as will make it ſo
ſtiffe that it will not be made into a ball, but remaine clammiſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
powder and paſte: then with a Peſtle ſtampe it gently into your Ring till
it be top full, being ſet upon an even board, then ſtampe it a little lower
in the middle then at the edges, and ſmooth it with a ſlight ſtone or
ſome round glaſſe, ſo ſet it in the Chimney Corner
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:978:17"/>to drye a day or two, and it is ready for your
worke.</p>
            <p>If you put a quarter of an ounce of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divert, and as much Salt
Peter mingled together with your Powder of Lead, and filings of Iron at your
firſt melting, it will melt ſomewhat ſooner, and with leſſe blowing:
beſides that the Sinder will part cleaner from the malleable mettall.</p>
            <p>And if you want Char-coales, you may burne Wood in an Oven, and when
it is red, and hath done ſmoaking, you may ſet up the Oven ſtone, and
dampe it.</p>
            <p>Or you may doe the like in an open Chimney, and dampe it in an
earthen Pot, or cover it with Aſhes, or dampe it in an hole in the ground, by
covering it with a cover, or with Aſhes.</p>
            <p>Any of theſe Coales will ſerve to make your aſſayes and
tryalls: as for directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for great workes here is no ſuch thing intended
in this little Booke: but onely to be ſure whether the worke will quit the
coſt: which if it will, then proviſion
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:978:17"/>for great workes will eaſily be brought to
paſſe.</p>
            <p>And if you want pots, you may bee at choiſe whether you will buy
the ſame at the Gold-ſmiths, or Potters in <hi>London,</hi> which ſell
<hi>Flanders</hi> melting Pots, of make them your ſelfe by this direction
following.</p>
            <p>Take right <hi>Flanders</hi> Iugges, ſuch as they uſually put
Bottle-Beere in, beate them to fine powder, and ſearce them fine as Meale:
Take of this meale foure pound, of the fine powder of <hi>Tobacco</hi> pipe
Clay one pound, temper them together with the red fattiſh water that
iſſueth out of an Horſe Dung-hill, beate it ſtrongly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a broad
board with a Rowling-pin, till it be ſtiffe Paſte, then faſhion your Pots
upon a peece of wood, turned like a Toppe, onely let the ſharpe end of the
Toppe be thicker and flatter than an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Toppe; then ſet them to drye
in your Chimney Corner a day or two: when you uſe them, ſet them in the
fire at the firſt kindling: and ſo let the Fire ſteale
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:978:18"/>upon them till they be red hot: then put in your
Mettle and ingredients, and cover it with a Tile-ſheard, or cover of Iron,
and ſo melt it downe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>Chap. 4.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Wherein is ſhewed the Operations for times.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Mettall may be melted downe like the Lead, onely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the
filings of Iron: but when it is melted it is not malleable, till it be
compounded with certaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions of other Mettalls, which I will not
declare, becauſe it is a ſecret of weight belonging to the Pewterers
Trade.</p>
            <p>And as for refining of it, I am ſure it cannot be done by any
artifice; for I ſuppoſe that I have tryed more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments about it, than
any 10. men in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:978:18"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> becauſe that I ſaw the
Refiners could not doe it: therefore I tooke the more paines and induſtry to
bring it to paſſe; which if I could have affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, I doe verily beleeve it
would have proved a rich Mettall: but the more I tryed the worſe I ſped,
for at the laſt of all I melted Gold and Silver equall parts with the Tinne,
thinking thereby to bring it downe into the Lead, and to make it to drive
faire, and refine kindly, but all was vaine, for the Tinne poiſoned and
conſumed ſome of my rich Mettalls.</p>
            <p>Now whereas there is no hope of any royall mettall ever to be gotten
out of this Minerall: to ſupply the ſhortneſſe of this Chapter, I will
ſhew a way how every one that hath a minde to meddle with theſe affaires,
may have good poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to enrich themſelves and their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity; and
be out of danger to undoe themſelves, or to damnifie themſelves in any
manner of value that is conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:978:19"/>
            <p>For my meaning is, in the taking in hand of this taske, to doe good
to all, and hurt to none: and that no man from henceforth ſhall need to bee
at a quarter of the charge, ſtudy, or labour, which I my ſelfe have
undergone.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſeeing that if the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious and exquiſite
wayes be taken in the deſigne that wit can attaine unto: yet it is but an
adventure; for ſometimes all the labour may be loſt, though not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, if
good heede be taken; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Mines maybe found, which will not quit
the charges to be wrought upon.</p>
            <p>Therefore as wiſe Merchants will not hazzard all in one Bottome,
ſo let this never be any mans deſigne totally: for now there is no ſuch
need but they may doe all that can bee done at ſuch ſpare times, as any
Gentleman, or man of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, uſually ſpendeth in Hawking, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
Gaming, or other pleaſures; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he neede but ſet a part of that time
for theſe purpoſes; having the moſt part of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:978:19"/>his worke done to his hands in this little
Booke.</p>
            <p>If the Refiners ſhall grudge at me, for diſcloſing ſome of
their ſecrets of their Trade, I will anſwer them in this manner: Firſt, I
my ſelfe have ſpent the time of divers Apprentiſhips in theſe affaires,
and therefore claime a priviledge to diſcloſe my experience for the
publicke benefits at my pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I affirme, that there can be no damage to any refiner, by
the divulging of theſe ſecrets: but on the contrary, a great probability of
much gaine to that trade: for that, here is nothing, but the skill to make the
aſſayes diſcloſed for the Searchers ſatisfaction, before he take in
hand great workes; which if he find cauſe ſo to doe, I adviſe him to
chuſe the beſt workman that he can get, and one that hath beene long
experienced in theſe Workes; and in ſo doing he ſhall proſper the
better in his deſigne: And if that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very yeare ſome of the increaſe of
that Trade ſhal be entertained in theſe affaires,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:978:20"/>as there is good probability they may; the reſt
will have cauſe to give me thanks for my paines, rather than opprobrious
ſpeeches.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 5.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Wherein is ſhewed the Operations of Iron.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S for the melting hereof, ſeeing that it is no worke to be done
in the Chimney corner, I will turne over the Reader to learne the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
thereof in every Countrey almoſt where he ſhall come.</p>
            <p>As for the Refining thereof it may be done in this manner: Take
filings of Iron two parts, Antimony one part, it will melt downe like your Lead
Oare: take the pure mettall, which will be much more brittle than the Lead was,
and melt it with foure times as much Lead as it weigheth, then refine it, as
before is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:978:20"/>taught: if you know the goodneſſe of your
Lead before, you may know the augmentation out of the Iron, which will not quit
the charges out of any Iron made in theſe Northerne Countries, nor yet out of
Spaniſh Iron: but what it may doe out of Iron made in the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Zone I
know not; but I conceive it may doe well, if any ſuch Iron can be found and
made in that Climate.</p>
            <p>It is true, that good gold may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted out of any Iron, but
not by any common way, but by a tedious, labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and coſtly way: and when
all is done, there will be no gaine, unleſſe it be in conceite, which
ſatisfieth no man, but thoſe who are of my diſpoſition, which thinketh
experience to bee the greateſt gaine that can bee in the world.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:978:21"/>
            <head>CHAP. 6.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Wherein is ſhewed the Operations of Copper.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, take your Oare, and breake it into little peeces, about
the bigneſſe of Hazell Nuts: then lay a Leere of ſmall Char-coales, an
inch thick in your Chimney Corner: then lay on your peeces of Oare, then lay on
more Char-coales an inch and an halfe thick upon the Oare, then kindle it, and
let the fire burne out of it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Then beate it into ſmall powder, and mingle it with your Sandiver,
and Salt-Peter, as you did your Lead, without any filings of Iron, and ſo
melt it downe as you did your Lead Oare: onely this difference muſt be
uſed, by reaſon that it is harder of fuſion than the Lead Oare: therefore
you muſt lay the bricks ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what wider than you did for the Lead,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:978:21"/>that it may hold more Coales: beſides that, you
muſt take the choyſeſt Coales that can be picked out, and no very ſmall
ones amongſt them: alſo you muſt have two paire of hand-Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and
two men to blow very ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo melt it downe.</p>
            <p>As for the refining it is needleſſe to ſhew the manner; for no
Copper in theſe Northerne Countries holdeth any royall Mettal, that is
conſiderable; neither En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh nor Danske Copper: yet in regard that in
ſome Mines in <hi>Hungarie,</hi> there is generated Gold, Silver, and Copper,
all in one maſſe of Oare: and alſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that if any Mines of Copper
ſhal be diſcovered in <hi>Virginia,</hi> or other ſouth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erne Countries,
there is ſome good probability that it may containe roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Mettal: therefore
I wil ſhew the manner how to refine it, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to part the Gold from the
Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, if it ſhal containe both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Firſt, melt one ounce of Copper with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:978:22"/>foure ounces of ſuch Lead, as you know the
goodneſſe of before: then refine it, and by the augmentation, you ſhall
know the worth of the royall mettall contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Copper.</p>
            <p>If you will trye whether the Copper contained any gold in it, put
the aſſay, <hi>viz.</hi> the little Bead or pearle of ſilver in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to good
Aqui-fort is well purified before, and if all diſſolve then the Coppcr held
no gold; but if it leave a black powder undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that is gold: for
Lead holdeth no Silver that hath any gold in it at all: therefore it is evident
that the Gold came out of the Copper.</p>
            <p>But if it happen, as often it doth in the refining of baſe
Mettals, eſpecially Tinne, Iron, and Copper, that the little Bead, or Pearle
remaining in the middle of the Teſt, is not bright and ſhining, like the
eye of a Bird, or Fiſh, but rough, blacke, and full of ſcurfe; then if it
be but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in quantity, an I that the Teſt be not cracked not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll of
lifts, then put to it ſome more of the ſame Lead, whereof you
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:978:22"/>know the goodneſſe, and drive it off a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
as you did at the firſt; and re-ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate this worke till the aſſay be
pure and cleane like a little Pearle, or Bead, as it ought to be.</p>
            <p>But if it happen that the Teſt is very foule, as often it commeth
to paſſe in the Refining of ſtrange Minerals, as <hi>Marcaſites,</hi>
and eſpecially thoſe which the Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralliſts call by the name of
<hi>Divells Dirt:</hi> Then there is no way but to let all coole; and then to
digge it out, and with more Lead to melt it anew in a Pot, and then to let it
coole, and then to breake the Pot, and to beate off the Cynder with an hammer,
till you come to the malleable Mettall, and you may be aſſured that no
royall Mettall will ſtay in the Cinder, but ſinke downe into the Lead,
through an attractive vertue betwixt them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:978:23"/>
            <head>CHAP. 7.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Wherein is ſhewed the Operations of Silver.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S for the melting thereof, when it is found in the Mine of Lead,
the Operation is taught in the Chapter of the Lead: but if it be found by it
ſelfe, or mixed with Gold without Lead, as many times it commeth to
paſſe, then it is to be beaten to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and mixed with Sandivere, and
Salt-Peter, without any filings of Iron, and ſo melted downe like the Lead
Oare; only the fire muſt be ſomewhat ſtronger.</p>
            <p>Then it is to be melted with foure times as much Lead, whereof you
know the goodneſſe: and ſo to be refined, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is declared.</p>
            <p>But whereas ſometimes this Oare is ſo ſtrongly mixed with
Sparre, and ſtony ſubſtances, that it cannot be ſeparated
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:978:23"/>therefrom, by any common manner of worke uſed
by the refiners; then this courſe is to be taken with it: Firſt, beate it
into ſmall powder; then waſh away with water the greateſt part of the
terreſtreity and filth: then drye the powder, and uſe it in this
manner.</p>
            <p>Firſt, melt foure ounces of Lead, and when it is melted put to it
foure ounces of quick-ſilver, made hot in another mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting pot: but let the
Lead be almoſt cold before you put to the Quick-ſilver: but yet it muſt
be done whilſt that the Lead is liquid.</p>
            <p>This done, caſt it into an Iron Morter, ſet warme before upon
Embers, and it will be like Pap; then preſently with a Peſtell, labour in
one ounce of your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or two at the moſt, till it be incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated; or
ſo much thereof as will incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate: for the ſtrong and earthy
ſubſtance will not incorporate with the Lead and Quicke-ſilver by any
Artifice whatſoever: but the ſilver, if any there be, will forſake the
Earthy and ſtony ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:978:24"/>and ioyne it ſelfe with the Lead and
Quick-ſilver by an attractive vertue. This done, put it altogether into a
mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Pot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with a little Sandivere, and Salt Peter, and melt it downe
as you did the Lead Oare: onely this muſt be obſerved, that the ſire
muſt be more milde at the fitſt a great deale, till the Quick-ſilver be
evapourated, and more ſtrong at the laſt, that all may ſlow well
together. Then take out the Pot, and let it coole; then breake it, and with an
hammer beate off all the Cynder and Scurfe, till nothing be left but malleable
mettall.</p>
            <p>Then refine it according to the common manner before declared, and
caſt up with your Penne the augmentation that is more than the Lead yeelded
of it ſelfe: and if there be no augmentation, then that Minerall ſtone
contained neither gold nor ſilver: for this is the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite way in
the world to reduce gold or ſilver, which is hard to be reduced to a
mettallicall body, through being ſtrongly mixed with either corroſive
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:978:24"/>ſubſtances, or any other filth which hindreth
his reduction: therefore if this way faile, you may ſet your heart at reſt
for the ſeeking out of any other devices whatſoever, though the
gliſtering ſparkes contained in the ſaid Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall doe never ſo
ſtrongly invite you; and you may conclude with the old ſaying, that all is
not gold that gliſters.</p>
            <p>But if it proſper, and yeelds any augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is
conſiderable: then if you deſire to know whether there was any Gold mixed
with the Silver, as oftentimes there is, where ſilver is ſound without
lead, then put the little bead, or pearle of ſilver, which remained on the
Teſt into <hi>Aqua-fortis,</hi> and if all diſſolve, then there is no
glold in that Mineral; but if a black powder remaine, then that is gold, and
the quantity may be found by further triall.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 8.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Wherein is ſhewed the Operations of gold: and reall experiments
whereby any man may preſently trye whether any peece of gold bee true or
counterfeit, without defacing or altering the forme thereof.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>As for the melting of it: if it be found
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:978:25"/>mixed with ſilver Oare, as oftentimes it
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to paſſe, then it is to be melted, refined, and parted from the
ſilver with <hi>Aqua-fortis,</hi> as is before declared, and if there bee not
five times as much ſilver, as there is gold in the compoſition, then you
muſt put to ſo much, or elſe the <hi>Aqua-fortis</hi> will not
diſſolve it.</p>
            <p>But if it be found in graines or powder, as often times it is, then
you muſt put to it Borax in ſtead of Sandiver and Salt Peter, and ſo melt
it downe as you did the other Oares before mentioned.</p>
            <p>Now for ſo much as this mettal is the moſt rich of all the
reſt, and moſt thirſted after, I wil enlarge my Diſcourſe for the
gaining of means to find it out: alſo I wil ſhew the reaſon why this
royal Mettal is many times found pure of it ſelfe, with little or no mixture
of other baſe mettal with it.</p>
            <p>And firſt, whereas it is oftentimes found in the ſand in Rivers,
let no man thinke that it could be generated there, but that the ſwift
mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the water from the high Mountaines, brought it thither, with earth
and altogether, till ſuch time as the motion of the Water grew more ſlow:
and ſo according to its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:978:25"/>being not able to carry forward ſtil both the
ſubſtances, did ſtill carry the earth with it, and let the heavier body
ſinke.</p>
            <p>Therefore I would have thoſe that have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to deale in the
hot Countries where gold is uſually generated, to make triall in all ſuch
Rivers which runne from great Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains with a ſwift courſe in ſuch
places, where the motion of the water beginneth to grow ſlow.</p>
            <p>And for this purpoſe he may have a little Bucket of Iron that will
not lie in the bottom, but on one ſide, which ſide muſt have a ſhooe
like a ſhovell; ſo that being drawne a little forward, as it lyeth in the
bottome it will fill it ſelfe with ſand: which you may try by grinding it
with Quick-ſilver whether it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine any gold: for if there be any gold in
the ſand, it will mixe with the quick-ſilver willingly: then you may waſh
away all the ſand, and ſtreine the quick-ſilver through a skinne of
leather, and if any gold be gathered into it, there wil remaine a Ball in the
Leather: then you may evapourate the Quick-ſilver from the Ball in a melting
pot, and ſo melt downe the gold with a little <hi>Borax.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:978:26"/>
            <p>Alſo ſometimes gold is found in Rivers in powder and graines,
farre diſtant from any mountaines of ſwift motion of water: this plainly
demonſtrateth that the earth therabout containeth gold: a thing uſually in
hot Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and that the water in that place had a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient motion to
weare away the earth, and to leave the gold behind, and this is manifeſtly
ſeene by experience where they waſh whole mountains of earth with water,
thereby to ſeparate the gold from it.</p>
            <p>Now whereas I have formerly affirmed that al mettals in general are
generated of the clam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and gluttenous part of the ſubterrancall vapours,
ariſing from from <hi>Bituminous</hi> and <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurous</hi>
ſubſtances, kindled in the bowells of the earth: it behooveth me to ſhew
how gold, ſuch a ſixed ſubſtance can be found pure of it ſelfe; and
not mixed with other baſe mettals.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon of this can be no other, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that all
other mettalls whatſoever will putrifie in the earth in length of time, &amp;
turne to earth againe; but <hi>gold</hi> wil never putrifie by reaſon of his
<hi>excellent compoſition,</hi> being made of a <hi>Balſamick
Sulphure,</hi> or fatnes, which is incombu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible, and diſtereth from the
<hi>Sulphure</hi> or <hi>fatnes</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:978:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>contained in the other <hi>mettalls,</hi>
even as naturall <hi>Balſome</hi> differeth from all other <hi>oyles,</hi>
fat ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: ſo that though it be an <hi>oyle</hi> in ſhew, yet it
wil ſink in water, whereas all other <hi>oyles</hi> wil ſwimme upon the top
of the water.</p>
            <p>And this is the cauſe why gold ſinketh ſo eagerly in
<hi>water,</hi> which may be proved by <hi>weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> a 20. <hi>ſhillings
peece</hi> of <hi>gold</hi> againſt his Braſſe <hi>weight,</hi> and then
letting his <hi>ſcales</hi> ſink in a Baſon of water 3. or 4. inches
deep, the <hi>gold</hi> wil there over-weigh the <hi>braſſe</hi> about 9.
or 10. grains, by reaſon that the <hi>braſse</hi> is more enclined to
<hi>ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> through the cumbuſtible <hi>fatnes</hi> or
<hi>ſulphure</hi> in its compoſition; and as for the 20. <hi>ſhillings
peece,</hi> ſo for any other peece of <hi>gold</hi> whatſoever according to
its ſeveral <hi>braſse</hi> weight you may in like manner try <hi>whether
it be true or counterfeit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now whereas the ſubſtance of <hi>gold</hi> is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to
putrifie in the earth by any length of time, it is probable enough that other
mettalls might be <hi>generated</hi> with it at the firſt, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<hi>putrified</hi> &amp; <hi>conſumed</hi> from it in length of time, leaving
the gold pure.</p>
            <p>For I have drawne Iron, or a ſubſtance much like to filings, or
<hi>attoms</hi> of Iron out of graine <hi>gold</hi> that was brought from
<hi>Gynnie</hi> with a Load-ſtone, which ſeemed to bee Iron not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:978:27"/>fully putrified, and turned into earth.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon why the hotter the Country is, the richer the
Minerals are, can be no other but the ſame, that roaſted meates are
ſweeter than boyled meates, or raw meates: the reaſon whereof is plaine,
for that the rawiſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſavory part is exhaled by the heate of the fire,
leaving the ſweeter part behind.</p>
            <p>Even ſo in hot Countries, all that part of the ſubterraneall
vapours, which here is condenſed into Lead, and other baſe mettalls, can
there have no leave to congeale, by reaſon of the heate: but is all or moſt
part thereof exhaled out of the Mines, leaving behind the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all mettals,
whoſe property is to coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with heat: whereas the property of the baſe
mettalls is to evapourate with heate and to congeale with cold.</p>
            <p>The contrary opinion to this; namely that the ſubſtance of the
beſt metals are convertible into royal mettals by heate and digeſtion, hath
filled the world with falſe Books and receipts in <hi>Alchimy,</hi> and hath
cauſed many men to ſpend much money, labour, ſtudy, and charges to no
purpoſe.</p>
            <p>For I know by good and long experience,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:978:27"/>and by many accurate trialls that Quick-ſilver
the moſt friendly <hi>mineral</hi> to the <hi>royall mettalls,</hi> can by no
meanes or Artifice whatſoever be fixed and coagulated into either of the
Royal Mettalls: alſo I have found ſince that no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of any credit or
Reputation teacheth any ſuch thing, but contrarily, condemneth all ſuch
operations to be falſe, vaine and frivilous.</p>
            <p>For the matter or ſubſtance of the Royal met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals is quite
contrary to that of the baſe met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, even as the fixed ſalt of any
vegetable is different from the <hi>volatill</hi> or fugitive <hi>ſalt</hi>
of the ſame. Yet I deny not but that by <hi>Art</hi> there may be drawne
ſome ſmal fixed part out of the baſe <hi>mettalls,</hi> and may be
converted into <hi>Royall Mettall,</hi> though with much labour, charges, and
loſſe.</p>
            <p>For as a Tree or other vegetable being bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, doth yeeld a fixed
<hi>ſalt</hi> or Aſhes: ſo the baſe <hi>mettalls</hi> doe containe in
them ſome ſmall quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of matter of the ſame nature that the royall
mettals are compounded of.</p>
            <p>And for the further ſatisfaction to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I will ſhew in
the next Chapter a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite to make reall and true gold abiding all
tryalls, and having all properties active and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:978:28"/>paſsive which true naturall gold hath: but in
ſtead of gaine, loſſe will be ready to follow the worke.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 9.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Wherein is ſhewed, how true and perfect gold may bee made by
Art with loſſe to the workman. Thus I wrought.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Tooke eight ounces of <hi>Regulus</hi> of Iron and Copper, made
as beneath is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, and 16. ounces of common <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blimate,</hi> bought
at the Apothicaries, &amp; made theſe ingredients into line powder: firſt,
ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and then I ground them well together upon a Marble ſtone, and
ſo put them into a a retort of glaſſe, and drew from them firſt an
Oile, then a ſubſtance like a Butter, and laſtly a yellow Sublimate,
tincted with the tincture of Iron and Copper, which yellow Sublimate I
rectified three or foure times, till it was very pure: then I mixed it with
equal parts of an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malgam</hi> of ſilver, and quick-ſilver, made as
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath is taught, and put it into another retort of Glaſſe, and forced
away all but the ſilver,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:978:28"/>which remained like yellow horn: this yellow
ſilver I <hi>amalgamed</hi> againe with new quick-ſilver, and ſet it in
gentle heat about a week, then in very ſtrong heat for 6. houres; ſo that
the <hi>quick-ſilver</hi> roſe up, and fell downe again upon the ſilver;
till ſuch time as that it had carryed up all the ſilver from the bottome of
the glaſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to branches like trees: then I melted downe the ſilver, and
ſined it, and parted it with <hi>Aqua-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> and had divers graines of
pure &amp; good gold abiding all tryalls: but the quantity would not pay for
halfe the charges and labour.</p>
            <p>I made the <hi>Regulus</hi> thus: I took 4. ounces of Iron in ſtub
nailes, and made them red hot in a cruſible: and then I put to it 8. ounces
of <hi>crude antimony,</hi> and melted it downe, and when it was well and thin
melted, I let it coole in the pot, &amp; ſo knockt off the <hi>regulus</hi>
from the lop, or cynder which lay upon the top of it, then I did the like with
4. ounces of Copper in thin plats: &amp; then I mixed equall parts of theſe
two, and melted them 3. or 4. times, every time caſting into the pot halfe an
ounce of ſalt peter, as it was in melting to purifie it, till it was pure
&amp; bright almoſt like ſilver, but yet brittle: ſo that I could beat it
in a Morter to fine powder.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:978:29"/>
            <p>The yellow ſilver that was like yellow horn, did <hi>Amalgam</hi>
with much difficulty, &amp; grinding with ſalt and vinegar, and ſome of it
was loſt, doe what I could: but the firſt ſilver was water ſilver,
which I bought at the refiners, out of which they had taken all the gold
before: this did <hi>Amalgam</hi> very eaſily, then I ſtrained it to a Ball
through a Leather skinne, and ſo mixed it with the yellow ſublimate that
was tincted yellow with the tincture of Iron and Copper.</p>
            <p>The proportion of the quick-ſilver to the ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was 5. or 6.
parts to one.</p>
            <p>If any one doubt the truth of <hi>Alchimy,</hi> he may be
ſatisfied by this triall; but in ſtead of gaine he ſhall pay for his
learning, by going away with loſſe.</p>
            <p>I doe not deny but there are workes of leſſe loſſe and
charge, yet none of them lucrous by reaſon of the change of times.</p>
            <p>For if any one will uphold me as good a leaſe, or purchaſe of
land, as I can prove by credible records, hath bin had in former times for an
ounce of gold, I will undertake to make an ounce of gold by Art to pay for it,
and yet have a good bargaine.</p>
            <p>But the difference of times hath confounded
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:978:29"/>this Art, as may appeare more plainly
beneath.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in ancient times a mans worke was not worth above a penny a
day, which now is worth two ſhillings ſixe pence a day, as may appeare by
ancient records for buildings, and the like: ſo that there is thirty to one
loſſe in the workmanſhip.</p>
            <p>Secondly, then coales, veſſels, &amp; other things neceſſary
for theſe affaires did coſt little, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the charge now.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when the gold was made, it would then have bought thirty or
forty times as much, either lands, leaſes, victuals, or work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip as
now.</p>
            <p>So that I conclude, that then the owners of this Art might gaine 30.
or 40. for one, and yet now they ſhall loſe extreamly.</p>
            <p>The cauſe that moved me to ſearch ſo much into theſe
affaires, was, becauſe I ſaw by the bookes, that ſo divers men in divers
ages, and in divers Countries did agree in one tale; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I conceived it
unpoſsible to be a lye, now I conceive it might be true, but that the times
have made an alteration.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:978:30"/>
            <head>CHAP. 10.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Wherein is ſhewed the operations for ſome of the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
Mineralls.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S for theſe baſe Minerals, <hi>viz. Cinabar</hi> naturall,
<hi>Antimony, Sulphur, Auripig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Arſenick, Talcum, Muſcovy glaſſe,
Emery,</hi> and many other things of like nature, becauſe they are of ſmall
value, and not worth the ſeeking for on ſet purpoſe, I will omit fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to diſcourſe of them: if any man ſhall find them, or any of them, by
accident, let him uſe his owne pleaſure, skill, and induſtry in the
proceeding of them.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, becauſe <hi>Cinabar naturall</hi> may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
much quick-ſilver, which is very uſefull for many things, &amp; may prove
as beneficial as a good mine of <hi>mettal,</hi> eſpecially if it ſhall be
found in great plenty: I wil therfore ſhew the <hi>refining
ſeparating,</hi>&amp; <hi>purifying</hi> of the ſame in ſmal proportion:
ſo that if it ſhal be found a <hi>profitable</hi> work, then the finder
thereof may proceed to a greater work. The firſt thing then to be done, is to
conſider of the weight therof: if it be very
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:978:30"/>ponderous, reddiſh in colour, and ful of cleare
ſtreakes, ſhining almoſt like the ſtreaks of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony,</hi> then
it is a good ſigne of a rich Mine.</p>
            <p>The firſt trial to be made thereof is to weigh a peece thereof,
and ſo put it into a gentle fire for an houre or two, in ſuch ſort that
it may onely be red hot; then to let it coole, and to weigh it againe, &amp;
ſo by the lightneſſe thereof, being compared with the former weight, you
may iudge ſomewhat of the richneſſe thereof.</p>
            <p>Then take a pound thereof, &amp; beat it into fine powder,&amp;
mingle it well with as much unſlect Lime, put it into a retort of glaſſe,
luted with Potters clay, and ſome horſe dung well beaten and tempered
together; then ſet it in a little furnace in your Chimny corner, &amp; force
it with fire 12. houres: let it be kept red hot the laſt 4. houres, and let
the noſe of the glaſſe enter into another glaſſe, filled almoſt
full of water, in ſuch manner that the vapours of the <hi>Cinabar</hi> muſt
needs enter into the water, for the better condenſation thereof into
quick-ſilver.</p>
            <p>This done, ſeparate your quick-ſilver in the bottom of the
water, and drie it, and weigh it; if you find the quantity conſiderable, then
you may proceed in this manner.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:978:31"/>
            <p>Firſt, make an hole in the earth with very good tempered clay that
wil hold water, and let it be narrow in the bottome, and wider and wider above
to the toppe to the breadth of 2. or 3. or 4. yards; then fill the Pit with
water, &amp; lay over it barres of iron of ſufficient ſtrength and
thickneſſe to beare the burden that muſt lye upon it; and let them lye
ſo neare toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that the ſtones &amp; wood cannot fal through: then lay
thereupon a leere of drye wood, and a leere of your red ſtone not broken
ſmall, and ſo doe againe till it be a yard thick or more, then give fire to
it on the wind ſide, and goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way out of the danger of the fumes, till you
ſee a far off that the fire is finiſhed and burned quite out.</p>
            <p>Then repaire to your worke, and let out the water through a pipe of
Lead, which ſhould be formerly laid almoſt at the bottome of the Pit, into
another pit neare to it, made ſo deepe that it may receive the water, and in
the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome you ſhall finde great ſtore of Quick-ſilver, if the Mine was
good.</p>
            <p>The water may be pumped up againe to ſerve the next day for the
ſame uſe; and you need but to take up a few of the bars of Iron every day
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:978:31"/>to goe downe into the pit, to take out your
Quick-ſilver, and ſo lay them downe againe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Wherein is ſhewed the waies to find out Pit-coales: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the
naturall cauſe of the generation of them, by a plaine demonſtration.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough this Minerall be of ſmall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, yet if a good Mine
thereof ſhall be diſcovered in ſome particular pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this land, the
benefit thereof will farre exceed the profit of any mettall Mine uſually
found in theſe Northerne Countries, by reaſon that wood is ſo greatly
decayed of late yeares, that were it not for this helpe many people would be in
danger to be ſtarved.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing therefore which I would have to be diligently
obſerved is; that this Mineral is uſually found in ground that is proane to
beare wood and thornes, and not in the very fertile grounds, nor yet in the
extreame barren grounds, but of an indifferent fertility, and in grounds that
are uſually flower in their growth in the Spring time, than the fertile
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:978:32"/>Champion countries by a week or a fortninght.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſaid grounds are proane to bring forth large Cattell,
and well horned: but not to feed the ſaid Cattell without a long time, nor
yet will they ever be very fat upon the ſame ground. Alſo the ſprings
iſſuing out of the ſaid grounds, are apt to colour the earth ruddy at
their Orifice, like unto the ruſt of Iron.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſaid ſpring water being boiled as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is taugh,
doth uſually yeeld a black reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>Alſo if you burie a new bowle of pure white Wood in the ſaid
grounds, from <hi>March</hi> till <hi>Midſummer,</hi> with the mouth
downeward, it wil be coloured blackiſh, with the ſubterraneal va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours.</p>
            <p>Alſo I had a receipt given me for this purpoſe by one, that for
his great experience, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent skill in naturall cauſes, ſeemed to be
one of <hi>Natures Darlings:</hi> which becauſe I have nor tryed, for want of
opportunity, I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it as a very probable ſigne, and give ſuch
Cautions, that any man may be ſure of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he trye his fortunes by
digging or boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or any chargeable way.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:978:32"/>
            <p>And this was his direction: <hi>about the middle of</hi> May,
<hi>when the ſubterraneall vapours are ſtrong, which may be diſcerned by
the Firne, which about that time will ſuddenly grow out of the earth in a
night or two, almoſt an handful in length, then take a pure white peece of
Tiffany, and wet it in the dew of the graſſe, which is all of that
ſprings growth, and not ſoyled with cattell, nor no other thing, then wring
out the dew from it; and do ſo five or ſixe times, and if there be coales
the Tiffany will be alittle blacked, and made foule with the ſooty vapours
ariſing through the Coales, and condenſed amongſt the dew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to be ſure not to be deceived, do thus: firſt trye it where
there are coales, and if ye find the ſignes above ſaid, yet truſt not to
the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, till you have tried where there is no Coales in ſome other
place, wherein it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth you to trye in divers places, till you find a place
where the Tiffiany is not ſoyled at all: then you may be ſure that the
experiment is true and unfailable.</p>
            <p>I admoniſh him that ſhal trie with the <hi>Tiffany</hi> upon the
dew, to let his hands be <hi>waſhed</hi> before with ſope &amp; hot water;
&amp; wiped with a pure white cloth, til they wil not foule the cloth at al;
elſe if they ſpend their <hi>mony</hi> in <hi>digging,</hi> &amp; find
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:978:33"/>nothing, they may thank their foule fingers for
that misfortune.</p>
            <p>As for the naturall cauſe of the generation of Coales, this
demonſtration following doth make it manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Take a peece of the blacke fat earth, which is uſually digged up
in the weſt Countrey, where there are ſuch a multitude of Firre trees
covered therewith, and which the people uſe to cut in the forme of Bricks,
and to drye them, &amp; ſo to burne them in ſtead of coales; uſe this
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as you did the other earth in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the booke, to
find out the natural cauſe of rocks, ſtones, and mettalls, and let it
receive the vapours of the cumbuſtible ſubſtances, and you ſhall find
this fat earth hardned into a plaine coale; even as you found the other Ieane
earth hardned into a ſtone.</p>
            <p>Whereby it appeareth that nature doth the ſame thing in the
generation of coales under the ground, by the indurating of a fat earth with
the ſubterraneal vapours which are apt to work a various effect according to
the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which they meet withall.</p>
            <p>Now wheras ſome of inquiſitive diſpoſitions wil deſire to
know the naturall cauſe of that fat
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:978:33"/>earth, generated in ſuch
<hi>ſubterraneall</hi> Cavernes, let them be pleaſed to conſider that
ſuch places in former times have bin the ſuperficies of the earth, and
afterward have bin covered by the ſea with other earth, which may be
demonſtrated by two wayes: firſt, it is evident that the mines of Coales
doe lye in ſome places higher, and in other places lower, lively reſembling
the <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies</hi> of the earth, which is never directly equal, but
every where various.</p>
            <p>Secondly, every one may ſee in the <hi>weſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> where
ſuch a multitude of Firre trees doe lie covered ſo deepe in the earth, that
the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies of the earth was deeper then it is now in former ages, when
thoſe trees were brought thither by the ſea: for it is evident that they
never grew there: firſt, for that there groweth no Firre trees in that
Countrey: ſecondly, for that they doe lie croſſe, and in ſuch uncooth
manner, that no humane ſtrength could ever imitate nor paralell by any device
whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Alſo they may ſee the power of the ſea to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the
ſuperficies of the earth, by the multitude of earth there laid ſo many
yards deepe upon the top of the trees.</p>
            <p>Alſo they may ſee that the ſea doth make the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:978:34"/>difference of the nature of earthes by its
vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious motion, as well as the unevenneſſe therof by hills and vallies:
for there they may ſee that ſome earth will burne, and ſome will not
burne, being both ſorts brought thither by the Sea, as appeareth evidently by
the former diſcourſes.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſea never reſting, but pepetually winning land in one
place, and loſing in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, doth ſhew what may be done in length of
time, by a continuall operation, not ſubiect unto ceaſing, or
intermiſsion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 12.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Wherein is ſhewed a perfect way to trye what colour any Berry,
Leafe Flower, Stalke, Root, Fruit, Seed, Barke, or Wood will give: alſo a
perfect way to make colours fixed, which will not abide the ordinary way.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere I muſt confeſſe a manifeſt digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from my
Subiect: yet in regard of the great benefit which this expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment may bring to
the Countrey, out of the new Plantations, and other places, where it is very
probable that many of theſe things be hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:978:34"/>and unknowne, I wil crave pardon, for that my
intent was chiefely to prevent the loſſe of thoſe things which may doe
much good, were it not through ignorance or negligence.</p>
            <p>Firſt then take halfe a pint of water, and halfe a pint of float,
made as beneath, 2. <hi>penny weight</hi> of <hi>Allom,</hi> 12. graines of
<hi>Tartar</hi> finely beaten, &amp; put all into a <hi>Tinne</hi> veſſel,
which is better than <hi>earth lead,</hi> or <hi>copper;</hi> ſet it on a
Trivet to diſſolve the <hi>Allom</hi> upon a gentle fire: as ſoone as it
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to boile, take a peece of white wollen cloth, well ſcoured with
Sope, fullers earth, or Lee, or altogether, to take out the greaſe of it,
being wel waſhed out with faire water, &amp; then dryed in the aire or Sun,
not by the fire: the cloth muſt weigh but halfe an ounce; then tie a thrid to
the end of the cloth, &amp; when the <hi>liquor</hi> beginneth to boile, then
put in the cloth, &amp; let it boile an houre; then take out the cloth, let it
coole, waſh it in two or three waters; then take any berry leafe, flower,
ſtalke, root, fruit, ſeed, barke, or wood, and bruiſe them wel; put them
in faire water, and boyle them with a gentle fire to extract the tincture; then
put in the cloth formerly prepared, which wil ſhew what Colour they will
give.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:978:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>To make the Float.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Boyle an Hogs-head of water, then caſt in a Buſhell of wheate
Branne, then draw the fire, then let it ſtand three or foure dayes, till it
grow ſowriſh.</p>
            <p>But for ſmall tryalls a little will ſerve, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
proportion betweene the Water and the Branne.</p>
            <p>A <hi>proportion</hi> muſt be obſerved in the allowing of all
ſtuffes before they receive their colours: Firſt, the <hi>proportion</hi>
of Allom to the water; which is one of Allom to 16. of water, and floate:
Secondly, the <hi>proportion</hi> of the <hi>Tartar</hi> to the <hi>Allom;</hi>
which is one of <hi>Tartar</hi> to 4. of <hi>Allom:</hi> Thirdly, the
<hi>proportion</hi> of <hi>Allom</hi> to the Cloath, which is one of
<hi>Allom</hi> to five of the Cloath.</p>
            <p>Note that all ſilkes muſt be Allomed cold, or elſe they will
loſe their luſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The way to finde what tincture is hidden in any vegetable or in
any part thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take the vegetable, being cut green, &amp; ſtamp and grind the
ſame, as if it were to make iuice thereof, then preſſe out the
ſuperfluous moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture; the remainder make up in Balls, and lay them up
together, that they may gather a little heat, but let them not heat too much,
for then
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:978:35"/>they will turne to dung: theſe being
ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fermented muſt be dryed, and afterwards u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as Oade is
uſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another way as Indico is made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Make a pit with Timber and boards, about a foote deep, and as wide,
and as long as you pleaſe, being well clayed in the bottome and ſides; then
fill this pit with any vegetable cut greene; then put as much water to it as
wil cover the herbes: let it ſtand expoſed to the Sunne two or three daies:
then with a plugge at the bottome draw out all the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and caſt it away:
then fill the pit againe with freſh water, and when it hath ſtood the like
time, draw it away as the former: this do ſo often, till you find that the
herbe will be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily brought into a muſsilage; then it muſt be trod, and
beaten with wodden inſtruments, like rammers, til it wil come al to a
muſsilage: then it muſt be taken and wrung through haire Sives, like
<hi>Caſſia Fiſtula</hi> extracted, to keepe the ſtalkes, and great
Fibres for paſsing through: afterwards the Muſsilage or pappe that
paſſeth through, muſt be dryed in the Sunne, and ſo formed into Cakes
like to Indico.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:978:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Another way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take the vegetable cut greene, and ſtampe and grind it: then take
an Hogs-head and fill it with halfe water, and halfe bruiſed herbes, ſet it
out of the Sunne, with the bung hole open two or three inches, till it firment
and worke like Wine or Beere: after it hath done working the Herbes will
ſinke, which at the firſt did ſwimme, and the liquor will grow a little
ſowriſh; then let it be ſet abroad in the Sunne, and brought into
vinegar, as wine and Beere is brought into vinegar, and then that colour can
never bee ſtained with other Vinegar or Vrine, becauſe it is ſufficiently
im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated, and his appetite ſatisfied with his owne proper Vinegar: when
his ſubſtance is thus turned into Vinegar, the cleare Vinegar muſt be
drawne from it, the remainder muſt be uſed as the former Indico, and ſome
water to that, to bee ſure to fetch out all his tartarous muſsilage, muſt
be put to the Vinegar, and dryed away in the Sunne, and ſo they come like
Indico: <hi>In tinctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramtartarizatam fixam Ide occulto in
manifeſtum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas Barkes, Woods, and Rootes are of a drye composition, and
will not fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:978:36"/>of themſelves with water like greene Herbes, or
vegetables: therefore they muſt be well ground, or thinne ſhaven, and there
muſt bee added in ſtead of Water, Iuice of Grapes, Peares, Apples, or Wort
made of Malt, or other graine, into which the Wood, Barke, or Rootes muſt be
put: let them ferment together, and afterwards be turned into Vinegar; then the
cleare Vinegar muſt be extracted: be reſidue of the tinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt bee
extracted with freſh water, and both of them muſt be breathed away in the
Sunne, as before, and ſo brought in his perfect tincture.</p>
            <p>By this which hath beene declared in this Chapter, it may appeare to
every one having an inquiſitive diſpoſition, what is the true na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
cauſe why ſome colours are fixed, and wil not ſtaine with vinegar, urine,
nor yet fade with the Aire; which hath in it a certaine ace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſity, or
ſharpe aiery ſalt of the nature of vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, which thoſe tinctures draw
to them, which have not their appetites fully ſatisfied before with ſuch
ſpirituall or aiery ſalts; and this is further manifeſt for that all
ſuch tinctures which are moſt firme &amp; fixed, &amp; are not ſubiect
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:978:37"/>to ſtaining or fading, being taſted upon the
tongue, may be felt ſomewhat ſharpiſh or ſowriſh.</p>
            <p>And the cauſe of this appetitive and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive vertue in colours
is no other but the very ſame which is betwixt the Load-ſtone and Iron: for
take the Load-ſtone, and burne it till all his blew vapour be exhaled, and
then he will draw no more Iron: thereby ſhewing plainely, that it was that
aiery ſalt, tincted with the venereall, or vegetable greenneſſe, which
the iron thirſted after, to ſatisfie his thirſty and drye nature and
conſtitution, which he got by his calcination and fuſion.</p>
            <p>And the like attraction may be diſcerned by the intellectuall
eyes, in anything that is ſtrongly burnt, ſo that all his ſpirits are
exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: as Lime will draw the aiery ſubſtance to him, and thereby quench
himſelfe: Alſo Tartar burned, and laid in the Aire, will draw the ſharper
part of the aire to it, and thereby diſſolve it ſelfe; and in ſumme,
all corporeal ſubſtances, the more they have loſt their ſpirituall
parts by naturall, or artificiall ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the ſtronger is their
Attractive vertue.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:978:37"/>
            <p>Now in ſtead of filling the Readers head with Proclamations, I
will conclude my Booke with giving caſe to his memory, by preſcribing what
neceſſaries he is to provide for the accompliſhing of his ſeverall
deſignes, in his Voyages or Plantations, whither his oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions ſhall
draw him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And firſt for him that will onely trie his fortunes in the
ſearching for Mineralls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He will neede nothing but two or three Pipkins, two or three
Vrinalls, an Iron Picke-Axe wel ſteeled, a Spade, and a Crow of Iron, if he
will be at the charge thereof: but there is no great neceſsity: alſo if he
bee not acquainted with the ſeverall Oares of mettalls, it will be convenient
that he take with him a little peece of every ſort of Oares: or ſo many
ſeverall kindes as he can get.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And for him that would proceede further, to trye the value of
them himſelfe, he muſt provide theſe things following.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Grate of Iron of a foote broad, ſome Bricks, two paire of good
hand-bellowes, a paire of Tonges, ſome Lead, Salt-Peter, Sandiver, Borax,
Flanders melting Pots, a
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:978:38"/>ring of Iron for the Teſt, an hatcher, or
hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw to cut wood: ſome good Aqua fortis, Weights and Scales: and if any
man be not active handed, he may have a man for a trifle to ſhew him the
Manuell practice in a day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he goe his voyage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And for him that will ſearch for Dying ſtuffes, hee may
ſee in the laſt Chapter what things he ſhall ſtand in neede of: Alſo
the other Chapters may be peruſed, whereby every one may be the better
accommodated for their ſeverall enterpriſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:978:38"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
